So, context engineering, possibly the
the single most popular expression in in
our world last year. Uh, context
engineering. So, look, the the the
output of an LLM, we know it's based
entirely on the input. It's stateless.
You give it an input. It produces an
output, the most likely tokens to follow
that input. And that input is sometimes
known as the context because it's all
the contextual information that we're
giving the LLM that it can use to
generate the output. Getting that input
right, getting the context right, that's
all we've got. That's it. The output is
only based on the input. So to say
getting this right is everything. It's
it's almost like obvious that of course
it's everything. That's all it has. It's
got that input. And so getting it right
is what this game is all about. We used
to call that prompt engineering.
Remember when prompt engineering a
couple years ago was with like like a
job that people could have and it was
the idea that you had to figure out the
best way to prompt an LLM. But really
that term prompt engineering has evolved
into this bigger term context
engineering which is recognizing it's
not just about the prompt. It's all
other things like the kind the tools you
give it and and other things that that
surround it to make sure that you are
doing the best job you possibly can do
to give the LLM all the right
information in the context so that the
output is most likely to achieve your
goal that that whole set of techniques
is what's known as context engineering
and there are a lot of different
components of what goes into this input
context this input to an LLM Um, first
of them, the the first thing and and one
of the first things you you learn about
when you're when you're calling an Alan
directly is there's a part of the
prompt, part of the text input that's
known as the system prompt that is the
most crucial, the the most general
information that frames the the overall
situation. What what role is this LLM
playing? What's its what's its overall
job? Is it an agent that's responsible
for writing code? Is it an agent that is
a customer support agent for an airline?
Whatever it is, that overall framing,
including the tone it should take and
the approach it should use, that goes
into something called the system prompt,
which usually is at the very beginning
of the information that is sent to the
LLM. There's then a set of descriptions
of the different tools that it has
access to. A bit like the way I said
that that if it put the word Python and
then something, it would be saying, I
want to run that in Python. and that
descriptions of the different tools,
that's also part of the the the context.
That's what might go in there next. And
of course, the more tools you want it to
have access to, the more space you will
fill up with these tools. And and some
people might say that that those tool
descriptions are actually part of the
system prompt. And that's really a
definitional thing. It doesn't
particularly matter if you think of them
as being part of the same thing or or
just two separate chunks. It's more just
about how you label it. But there in for
this diagram anyway I'm saying there is
the overall framing followed by the
tools and then there's something that is
sometimes called the memory. And this is
basically information that you want to
persist across potentially multiple
different conversations. Some people
call this long-term memory or
medium-term memory, but this is
typically general resources that can
change over time, but that you'd want to
always be able to come back to. And then
there is the big part of it which is
basically the the the actual input that
you're sending to the LLM. But remember
because of the this way that we have
this this trick that that allows us to
give the illusion of a memory. What we
send can't just be the most recent
message that we want to send the LLM.
It's got to be the entire conversation
so far. It's got to be the very first
message that we sent and then its reply
and then our follow- on message and its
reply to that. So all of the messages
that formed this conversation to the LLM
all need to fit next in the context.
They all need to be squeezed in next.
And that also needs to include any
reasoning that the LLM has done, any of
the these tokens that it generates to
describe its thought process. There are
there are sometimes when you you can
actually not not include that, but
generally speaking, that does tend to
get included here. and it's it's replies
and then if it's generated code then
that code that it's generated needs to
go here. If it's called tools then the
tools it's decided to call and the
output from calling those tools that all
has to go in here. All this information
forms the input and when it's generating
the output it will be generating output
that's consistent with this entire
conversation history of the full
conversation so far. So all of that
makes up the single input to the LLM
because it's stateless. It needs to get
this entire package that you see here in
order to be able to generate the the
most likely next token that will be
consistent with our objective. And
there's something else in the coding
agents that we're going to be working
with. There is a special thing that gets
included in there too which is really I
guess part of memory but I'm going to
show it as a separate separate line item
if you will a separate thing that gets
shoved in here and it is a special file
and it's often called agents.md
and you may well know about this already
but we'll be looking at it and we'll be
talking a lot about what makes a good
one and a bad one and so on and you can
think of this as being like part of the
memory it's it's a resource that
persists or you can say this is
something something extra RA in addition
to the other parts of memory. This
agents.m MD is something special. And of
course, if you're working with claude
code, it's in fact claude.md. And with
anti-gravity, it's gemini.md. But these
are all what we generally think of as
the agents.md files. And these are files
that we particularly use with coding
agents that describe special things
about the project we're working on,
particular coding standards or things
about our objective, something that we
want to be in the memory of the AI agent
while it's writing code for us. That is
agents.md,
a special file we write that gets shoved
in the context every single time. Ah, I
can hear you correcting me there. You
know that it's not every single time.
It's more complicated than that. But
never fear, we will get to that. We will
get to that. But for now, consider it to
be every single time. All right. So,
that is the context. That's what context
engineering is all about. And as you
probably also know, but there's no harm
in us going through it again. There is
of course this idea of a context window
which is to say that an LLM has a limit
to how many tokens can be fit in this
context before it runs out of room
because an LLM is designed to be able to
look back over a number of different
tokens as it's forming its predicted
next tokens. And each LLM can only look
back so far that they they're only large
enough to look back a certain amount of
tokens. And if you try and pass in more
tokens than its maximum context window,
it will fail. That is considered a
break. It can't handle it and it will be
an error. It's the maximum number of
tokens that it can examine in its input
in order to predict the next tokens.
That's called it's sometimes just called
the context window or the context window
limit, but it is the maximum size of
this this context that's passed in. And
so it needs to fit within this context
window. And that's something which many
of us agonize over constantly. And
people people obsess over this this
context limits the the fact that that
you can't go over it. But in fact, it's
worth keeping in mind that in a lot of
cases, just having too much in the
context, even if you're not yet at the
limit, it can still cause performance to
degrade. And I'm using performance
there, not in the kind of speed sense,
not not performance like like we
software people sometimes say. I'm
talking about the accuracy, the quality
of the results, that kind of performance
that can start to degrade. You get
poorer results. You start to lose
coherence. It starts to forget things as
you fill up the context more and more.
So, even if you're not yet at the limit,
even if you haven't filled up the
context window, you might start to see
degrading performance if you're shoving
too much in the context. And conversely,
you tend to get the best performance at
the very start of your conversation when
the the context is is super empty and
it's only got a little bit to pay
attention to. And so, that's something
to be very cognizant of. It's not just a
binary, have you got too much, it fails.
There's also a sense of of less less is
more when it comes to filling up the
context. Okay. Now, I've been saying
that the LLM fails when the context
window gets filled up. And you're
probably thinking, well, I I don't think
it fails. I think it it does compacting.
You've probably experienced compacting
before. That's actually a feature built
in to things like clawed code, which is
that rather than allowing it to fail, it
detects when the context window is
almost filled up and it runs this
process that essentially looks back at
the whole conversation history and then
summarizes it and replaces everything
with a little summary of what was there
before, freeing up lots of space in the
context history in the in the
conversation history. And and this is
something which which is very common and
it's also something which is feared by
by people like you and me a lot because
it it changes the game suddenly. The
challenge with compacting is that we are
trusting the LLM to do a good job of
figuring out what's important and what's
not important from the conversation
history. And often it does a good job
but sometimes it doesn't. Sometimes it
misses an important thing uh that that
we care a lot about that we that we told
it about during the conversation that
gets removed when it's summarizing and
as a result uh the LLM appears to forget
something that we've told it or it makes
the same mistake twice which is super
frustrating and because of this people
people have have tended to fear the
compactor don't like it when it compacts
and often you'll you'll find that people
and I I do this a lot myself rather than
let it compact I will look at what's
happened before I will stop the agent
and then I will rewrite my file like
agents.mmd that I mentioned before and
then start it up again fresh making sure
that I've kept careful note of
everything that's happened that it needs
to know about. So people do tend to fear
the compacting process and like to stop
it and refresh it and rewrite it because
there's a lack of trust for how
compacting works. There's a particular
fear as well for if it if it's going to
run compacting whilst it's in the middle
of doing something. And that's something
that that you can get around by forcing
it to compact at a good time. And that's
a bit a bit different. What I'm talking
about is just a general fear of
compacting. But the truth of the matter
is compacting has got a lot better in a
just recent history. And now as of 2026,
uh there is less reason to fear the
compactor. It does a really good job.
So, I am still of the old guard that I
do tend to still like to stop and
summarize my agents.mmd, but I know that
some of that is my stubbornness at this
point and that often you can just trust
the compactor. And so, I'm here to tell
you, don't be like me. At least start
out by trusting the compactor. Trust
compacting. Let it do its thing. and it
will often do a really fine job of
summarizing the conversation history,
keeping relevant stuff that it needs to
remember and freeing up tons of space
for more conversation. That's what it
does and it tends to do it well. And
maybe one more point to mention on
context windows is just to tell you the
the context window size of of different
major models. So, uh OpenAI's uh GPT 5.2
two that that we used yesterday. Uh that
has a context window of 400,000
tokens. 400,000 tokens. Uh Claude, the
Claude Sonnet 45 called Opus 45 that has
200,000 tokens. So about half. And
Gemini and and the Gemini in in
anti-gravity for from Google that has a
context window of a million tokens. A
million tokens. Much greater. So these
these are the limits if you it can't go
above that number. But it's again worth
pointing out that you'll see degrading
performance as you start to put more in
the context. So personally I I don't
overobsess about these max context
window sizes because I'm more interested
in in in how is performance affected by
putting more into the context. And I
find across all the models that having
less in the context gets better results.